A Guide to the Records of the Mid-Atlantic Chapter of the Medical Library Association.
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Records of the Mid-Atlantic Chapter of the Medical Library Association. 1953-2008
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
2005/Mar/05
7 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Tompkins-McCaw Library was designated as the depository for MAC/MLA records in 1998.
Collection also contains the following accession numbers: 2001/Nov/15, 2000/Jul/05.
Separated Materials
Additional records of MAC and its predecessors can be found in the records of the Medical Library Association at the National Library of Medicine, Bethesda, Maryland.
Custodial History
MAC officers and committee chairs retained the records of the organization until they were gathered together through the efforts of Diane McKenzie and the MAC Records Task Force.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Mid-Atlantic Chapter (MAC) of the Medical Library Association (MLA) began on Saturday, March 29, 1952, when eighty-six medical librarians from the District of Columbia, Maryland, Virginia, and West Virginia agreed to form the Washington DC, Area Medical Library Group. The three librarians behind this meeting are considered MAC's founders: Estelle Brodman, Scott Adams, and Ida Marian Robinson.
At the second meeting, in 1953, a study committee recommended that the group affiliate with the Medical Library Association, but retain semi-independent status. Passage of the 1964 Library Assistance Act led to grouping Washington DC, Virginia, Maryland, West Virginia, and North Carolina together as Region IV. Similarly the Washington area group expanded its boarders to take in North Carolina, formerly associated with a southern group, and West Virginia. In the early years the group had no formal officers although a chair was designated to handle the details of the annual meetings. The meetings rotated between the various states of the group.
At the 1971 annual meeting, the group's name was changed to the Mid-Atlantic Regional Group (MARG). Three years later the group began discussions to establish a more formal organizational framework to coincide with discussions held at the national level. MLA adopted a new group structure in 1979 that brought additional changes for MARG.
In 1981 MARG was reorganized into a chapter, the Mid-Atlantic Chapter (MAC). It completed its mandatory three-year test for compliance with MLA chapter guidelines in 1985. The semiannual newsletter, MAC Messages, began in 1984. The newsletter would become quarterly in 1986, then bimonthly in 1990. MAC Messages was published online beginning in 1995.
Additional information on the history of MAC is available on the organization's web site.
Scope and Content
The Collection includes the group's many committee reports (financial, membership, executive, etc.) as well as Board of Directors minutes and publications. The bulk of the collection documents the organization's annual meetings. Included are the packets, schedules, and agendas as well as planning documents for most of the annual meetings. In addition the records include membership roles, course descriptions for professional development and distance education courses, financial records, unit histories as well as copies of the MAC Messages newsletter. The materials date from the mid-1950s to the present. Most of the items dating from before 1974 are photocopies.
Arrangement
The Collection is arranged in three subgroups. Original file designations and collection organization was retained where possible. Collection was compiled from the records of MAC officers and members.
List of Series
Subgroup 1: Board of Directors
Series 1: Minutes, Working Papers, and Reports
Series 2: Minutes of MAC Business Meetings
Series 3: Financial and Treasurers Reports
Series 4: MAC topic/subject Files
Subgroup 2: Standing Committees
Series 1: Annual Meeting
Subseries 1: Annual Meeting Records
Annual Meeting Evaluation
Subseries 2: Photographs
Subseries 3: Memorabilia
Series 2: Membership and Recruitment Committee
Subseries 1: Administrative Records
Subseries 2: MAC Membership Directory
Series 3: Professional Development Committee
Series 4: Communication Committee
Subseries 1: Administrative Records
Subseries 2: MAC Messages
Series 5: Honors and Awards Committee
Series 6: Strategic Planning Committee
Subgroup 3 Other Committees and Task Forces
Series 1: Nominating Committee
Series 2: Government Relations
Subgroup 4 Historical Materials
Series 1: Historical Information related to MAC
Series 2: MAC/MLA Anniversaries
Contents List
- Board of Directors
  This subgroup contains the records of the MAC governing board including executive committee minutes, reports, communications, and correspondence. Most materials date from the post-1980 period when the group adopted a more formal governing structure.
  - Executive Committee Working Papers and Reports 1981-2007
    This series contains the Board of Directors meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence.
    - Executive Committee 1981 (Box-folder 1.1)
    - Executive Committee 1982 (Box-folder 1.2)
    - Executive Committee 1983 (Box-folder 1.3)
    - Executive Committee 1984 (Box-folder 1.4)
    - Executive Committee 1985 (Box-folder 1.5)
    - Executive Committee 1986 (Box-folder 1.6)
    - Executive Committee 1987 (Box-folder 1.7)
    - Executive Committee 1988 (Box-folder 1.8)
    - Executive Committee 1989 (Box-folder 1.9)
    - Executive Committee 1990 (Box-folder 1.10)
    - Executive Committee 1990-91 (Box-folder 1.11)
    - Executive Committee 1991-92 (Box-folder 1.12)
    - Executive Committee 1992-93 (Box-folder 1.13)
    - Executive Committee 1993-94 (Box-folder 1.14)
    - Executive Committee 1994-95 (Box-folder 1.15)
    - Executive Committee 1995-96 (Box-folder 1.16)
    - Executive Committee 1996-97 (Box-folder 1.17)
    - Executive Committee 1998-99 (Box-folder 1.18)
    - Executive Committee 1999-2000 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - Executive Committee 2000-01 (Box-folder 1.20)
    - Executive Committee 2001-02 (Box-folder 1.21)
      - Executive Board Minutes January 11, 2002
      - Executive Board Minutes September 10, 2002
    - Executive Committee 2002-03 (Box-folder 1.22)
      - Executive Board Minutes February 21, 2003
      - Executive Board Minutes September 5, 2003
    - Executive Committee 2003-04 (Box-folder 1.23)
      - Executive Board Minutes February 6, 2004
      - Executive Board Minutes September 24, 2004
    - Executive Committee 2004-05 (Box-folder 1.24)
      - Executive Board Minutes January 28, 2005
      - Executive Board Minutes September 9, 2005
    - Executive Committee 2005-06 (Box-folder 1.25)
      Includes photographs of the September 15, 2006 board meeting.
      - Executive Board Minutes March 3, 2006
      - Executive Board Minutes September 15, 2006
    - Executive Committee 2006-07 (Box-folder 1.26)
      - Executive Board Minutes February 7, 2007
      - Executive Board Minutes September 7, 2007
  - Annual Business Meeting Minutes 1979-80, 1982-2006
    This series contains copies of the annual business meeting minutes. Some are the published version which appeared in MAC Messages.
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1979 (Box-folder 1.26)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1980 (Box-folder 1.27)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 1.28)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1983 (Box-folder 1.29)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1984 (Box-folder 1.30)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1985 (Box-folder 1.31)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1986 (Box-folder 1.32)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1987 (Box-folder 1.33)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1988 (Box-folder 1.34)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1989 (Box-folder 1.35)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1990 (Box-folder 1.36)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1991 (Box-folder 1.37)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1992 (Box-folder 1.38)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1993 (Box-folder 1.39)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1994 (Box-folder 1.40)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1995 (Box-folder 1.41)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1996 (Box-folder 1.42)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1997 (Box-folder 1.43)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1998 (Box-folder 1.44)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 1999 (Box-folder 1.45)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2000 (Box-folder 1.46)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2001 (Box-folder 1.47)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2002 (Box-folder 1.48)
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2003 (Box-folder 1.49)
      - Minutes October 28, 2003
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2004 (Box-folder 1.50)
      - Minutes October 15, 2004
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2005 (Box-folder 1.51)
      - Minutes October 6, 2005
    - Business Meeting Minutes 2006 (Box-folder 1.52)
      - Minutes October 15, 2006
  - Financial and Treasurers Reports 1976-2000
    This series contains the annual, semi-annual financial reports, tax information and other financial reports.
    - Treasurers Report 1976-1977 (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Treasurers Report 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2.2)
    - Treasurers Report 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2.3)
    - Treasurers Report 1982-1983 (Box-folder 2.4)
    - Treasurers Report 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2.5)
    - Treasurers Report 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2.6)
    - Treasurers Report 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2.7)
    - Treasurers Report 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2.8)
    - Treasurers Report 1994, 1998 (Box-folder 2.9)
    - Treasurers Report 1999, 2000 (Box-folder 2.10)
    - Financial Planning Task Force Report 1997-2004 (Box-folder 2.11)
      This is the work of the Financial Planning Task Force. It contains committee reports and other documents generated by the Task Force.
    - Financial Reports 1981-1990 (Box-folder 2.12)
      Financial reports showing five year trends in the MAC budget.
    - Financial Statements and Tax Forms 1982, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 2.13)
      Contains several financial reports from area accountants.
    - Interest and Dividend Tax Compliance Act 1983 (Box-folder 2.14)
    - 509(c)(3) status (Box-folder 2.15)
      This folder contains the documents and correspondence needed to earn Tax Free status for MAC.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 2.16)
      This folder contains documents regarding the IRS and 509(c)(3) status.
  - MAC Topic/Subject Files
    - ADA policy and requirements 1993 (Box-folder 6.11)
      Included are the recommendations and accommodations for compliance with the ADA.
    - MAC Brochures (Box-folder 6.12)
      Chapter brochures
    - Building Power, The Art of Influence 1993 (Box-folder 6.13)
      by Elizabeth Poage Baxter.
    - Constitution and Bylaws (Box-folder 6.14)
      This folder includes group bylaws and proposed changes.
    - Goals and Objectives 1993-1994, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 6.15)
    - MAC Internship 1996-1998 (Box-folder 6.16)
      Proposal, documents, and advertisement for MAC Internship
    - Journal Club (Box-folder 6.17)
    - MAC Letterhead (Box-folder 6.18)
      Letterhead and envelopes
    - MAC Logo 1993 (Box-folder 6.19)
      Logo designs and proposals
    - Needs Assessment Survey (Box-folder 6.20)
      This folder includes Needs Assessment surveys and their results.
    - MAC Pin 1998 (Box-folder 6.21)
      Designs and proposals for the MAC Pin.
    - Platform for Change (Box-folder 6.22)
      Included are discussion questions, and copies of the booklet.
    - Policy Procedure Manual 1992 (Box-folder 6.23)
      This folder includes correspondence, proofs and working copies of the Policy Procedure Manual.
- Standing Committees
  The standing committees of MAC are specified by the organization's Bylaws and include Annual Meeting, Membership and Recruitment, Professional Development, Communication, Honors and Awards, and Strategic Planning
  - Annual Meetings 1953-2007
    This series includes information on MAC's annual convention including printed programs, flyers, handouts, information packets, published reports on annual meetings. Some were transfered directly from the records creators and others were compiled after the fact.
    - Annual Meeting Records 1953-2007
      - Baltimore, MD 1953 (Box-folder 2.17)
      - Richmond, VA 1955 (Box-folder 2.18)
      - Washington, DC 1959 (Box-folder 2.19)
      - Richmond, VA 1962 (Box-folder 2.20)
      - Baltimore, MD 1963 (Box-folder 2.21`)
      - Bethesda, MD 1964 (Box-folder 2.22)
      - Charlottesville, VA 1964 (Box-folder 2.23)
      - Baltimore, MD 1966 (Box-folder 2.24)
      - Washington, DC 1967 (Box-folder 2.25)
      - Richmond, VA 1968 (Box-folder 2.26)
      - Washington, DC 1969 (Box-folder 2.27)
      - Baltimore, MD 1970 (Box-folder 2.28)
      - Winston-Salem, NC 1971 (Box-folder 2.29)
      - Cockeysville, MD 1973 (Box-folder 2.30)
      - Arlington, VA 1974 (Box-folder 2.31)
      - Morgantown, WV 1975 (Box-folder 2.32)
      - Durham, NC 1976 (Box-folder 2.33)
      - Richmond, VA 1977 (Box-folder 2.34)
      - Annapolis, MD 1978 (Box-folder 2.35)
      - Morgantown, WV 1979 (Box-folder 2.36)
      - Asheville, NC 1980 (Box-folder 2.37)
      - Norfolk, VA 1981 (Box-folder 2.38)
      - Baltimore, MD 1982 (Box-folder 2.39)
      - White Sulfur Springs, WV 1983 (Box-folder 2.40)
      - Washington, DC 1984 (Box-folder 2.41)
      - Winston-Salem, NC 1985 (Box-folder 2.42)
      - Charlottesville, VA 1986 (Box-folder 2.43)
      - Baltimore, MD 1987 (Box-folder 2.44)
      - Charleston, WV 1988 (Box-folder 2.45)
      - Rockville, MD 1989 (Box-folder 2.46)
      - Raleigh, NC 1990 (Box-folder 2.47)
      - Williamsburg, VA 1991 (Box-folder 2.48-49)
      - Towson, MD 1992 (Box-folder 2.50-53)
      - Morgantown, WV 1993 (Box-folder 2.54-55)
      - Asheville, NC 1994 (Box-folder 2.56)
      - Richmond, VA 1995 (Box-folder 2.57-60)
      - Columbia, MD 1996 (Box-folder 3.1-3)
      - Arlington, VA 1997 (Box-folder 3.4-8)
      - Pittsburgh, PA 1998 (Box-folder 3.9-12)
      - Wilmington, NC 1999 (Box-folder 3.13-15)
      - Roanoke, VA 2000 (Box-folder 3:16-17)
      - Ocean City, MD 2001 (Box-folder 3.18-19)
      - Washington DC 2002 (Box-folder 3.20)
      - Philadelphia, PA 2003 (Box-folder 3.21)
      - Wilmington, NC 2004 (Box-folder 3.22)
      - Charlottesville, VA 2005 (Box-folder 3.23)
      - Atlanta, GA 2006 (Box-folder 4.1-2)
      - Baltimore, MD 2007 (Box-folder 4.3)
    - Annual Meeting Evaluations
      This subseries includes the evaluation for MAC meetings. These reports may also be found within the Annual Meeting Records subseries and in the Board of Directors subgroup.
      - Program Evaluations 1986-1989, 1991-1992, 1994-1997, 1999, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 4.4)
    - Annual Meeting Photographs
      This series contains photographs taken at annual meetings.
      - Photographs 1991 (Box 7)
      - Photographs 1996 (Box 7)
      - Photographs 1997 (Box 7)
      - Photographs 1998 (Box 7)
      - Photographs 2000 (Box 7)
      - Photographs 2002 (Box 7)
      - Photographs 2003 (Box 7)
    - Memorabilia 1994, 1997, 1998, 2002, 2004, 2007, Bags, pins and other items
      Materials given out at MAC annual meetings
  - Membership and Recruitment 1990-1997, 1999-2000
    This series contains annual reports, membership lists, and other documents generated by the committee.
    - Administrative Records 1990-2005
      - Membership Committee Reports 1990 (Box-folder 4.5)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1991 (Box-folder 4.6)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1992 (Box-folder 4.7)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1993 (Box-folder 4.8)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1994 (Box-folder 4.9)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1995 (Box-folder 4.10)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1996 (Box-folder 4.11)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1997 (Box-folder 4.12)
      - Membership Committee Reports 1999 (Box-folder 4.13)
      - Membership Committee Reports 2000 (Box-folder 4.14)
      - Membership Committee Reports 2005 (Box-folder 4.15)
    - Membership Directories 1989-2003 (Box 6)
      This subseries contains the published MAC membership directories.
  - Professional Development Committee
    This series contains course descriptions, proposals, surveys, and other documents created by the committee. It was previously known as the Continuing Eucation Committee.
    - Professional Development Committee 1986 (Box-folder 4.16)
    - Professional Development Committee 1989 (Box-folder 4.17)
    - Professional Development Committee 1990 (Box-folder 4.18)
    - Professional Development Committee 1991 (Box-folder 4.19)
    - Professional Development Committee 1992 (Box-folder 4.20)
    - Professional Development Committee 1993 (Box-folder 4.21)
    - Professional Development Committee 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4.22)
    - Professional Development Committee 1996 (Box-folder 4.23)
    - Professional Development Committee 1997 (Box-folder 4.24)
    - Professional Development Committee 1998-1999 (Box-folder 4.25)
    - Professional Development Committee 2001-2002 (Box-folder 4.26)
    - Professional Development Committee 2002-2003 (Box-folder 4.27)
    - Professional Development Committee 2003-2004, Includes CD of documents (Box-folder 4.28)
    - MLA Chapter Project 1996 (Box-folder 4.29)
      The Professional Development Committee submitted its work in developing a counseling service for members interested in applyiny to MLA's Academy of Health Information Professionals (AHIP) for the MLA Chapter Project of the Year Award
  - Communications Committee 1989-1991
    This series contains annual reports, survey, publications, and other documents. The committee was formerly known as the Publication Committee.
    - Administrative Records
      - Publication Committee 1984-1985 (Box-folder 4.30)
      - Publication Committee 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4.31)
      - Publication Committee 1988 (Box-folder 4.32)
      - Publication Committee 1989 (Box-folder 4.33)
      - Publication Committee 1990 (Box-folder 4.34)
      - Publication Committee 1984-1985 (Box-folder 4.35)
      - Directory of the Publications of the Chapters of the Medical Library Association 1989 (Box-folder 4.36)
      - MAC Web Site 1998-2003 (Box-folder 4.37)
    - MAC Messages
      MAC Messages was initially a print only publication. A web version of MAC Messages is available for 1984, 1995, 1996, and 1998 to the present.
      - Vol. 1-4 1985 (Box-folder 4.38)
      - Vol. 5-8 1986 (Box-folder 4.39)
      - Vol. 9-12 1987 (Box-folder 4.40)
      - Vol. 13-16 1988 (Box-folder 4.41)
      - Vol. 17-19 1989 (Box-folder 4.42)
      - Vol. 19-24 1990 (Box-folder 4.43)
      - Vol. 25-31 1991 (Box-folder 4.44)
      - Vol. 32-36 1992 (Box-folder 4.45)
      - Vol. 37-42 1993 (Box-folder 4.46)
      - Vol. 43-48 1994 (Box-folder 4.47)
      - Vol. 49-54 1995 (Box-folder 5.1)
      - Vol. 55-60 1996 (Box-folder .52)
      - Vol. 61-66 1997 (Box-folder 5.3)
      - Vol. 67-72 1998 (Box-folder 5.4)
      - Vol. 73-78 1999 (Box-folder 5.5)
      - Vol. 79-84 2000 (Box-folder 5.6)
      - Vol. 85-90 2001 (Box-folder 5.7)
      - Vol. 91-96 2002 (Box-folder 5.8)
      - Vol. 97, 99-101 2003 (Box-folder 5.9)
        Vol. 98 was not printed. Vol. 99 March/April mistakenly printed as Vol. 99.
      - Vol. 102-106 2004 (Box-folder 5.10)
      - Vol. 107-112 2005 (Box-folder 5.11)
      - Vol. 113-116 2006 (Box-folder 5.12)
      - Vol. 117-120 2007 (Box-folder 5.13)
  - Honors and Awards
    This series includes records from the Honors and Awards Committee including correspondence, award nominations, reports and other materials documenting the various recognitions confered by MAC.
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1991-1993 (Box-folder 5.20)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1994-1995 (Box-folder 5.21)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1995-1996 (Box-folder 5.22)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1997-1998 (Box-folder 5.23)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5.24)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1999-2000, Includes one 3.5 inch diskette (Box-folder 5.25)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 2000-2001, Includes CD (Box-folder 5.26)
    - AHIP 1995, 1997 (Box-folder 5.27)
    - Honors and Awards Budget 1994-1994, 2001 (Box-folder 5.28)
    - Certificate Drafts 1991-1993 (Box-folder 5.29)
    - Chapter Project Award 1995 (Box-folder 5.30)
    - Estelle Brodman Award 1991-1995 (Box-folder 5.31)
    - Honors and Awards Other Chapters 1990-1992 (Box-folder 5.32)
    - MAC Bibliography 1997 (Box-folder 5.33)
    - Marguerite Abel Service Recognition Award 2001 (Box-folder 5.34)
    - Needs Assessment 1993 (Box-folder 5.35)
    - New Librarian AwardHonrs and Awards Committee 1993 (Box-folder 5.36)
    - Retirees 1994-1997 (Box-folder 5.37)
  - Strategic Planning
    Stategic Planning began as a Task Force and was subsequently made a standing committee. Records include correspondence, reports, and meeting minutes.
    - Strategic Planning Task Force 1984-1989 (Box-folder 5.38)
    - Strategic Planning Task Force 1990-1994 (Box-folder 5.39)
- Other Committees and Task Forces
  - Nominating Committee
    - Nominating Committee 1999-2000 (Box-folder 6.1)
    - Nominating Committee 2004 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Nominating Committee 2007, CD with three zip files (Box-folder 6.3)
  - Government Relations Committee 1987, 1990, 1992 (Box-folder 6.4)
  - Records Task Force - Archives (Box-folder 6.5)
- Historical Materials
  Copies of documents and correspondences that related to the formative years of MAC. Some records in these files are photocopies of material found in the records of the Medical Library Association at the National Library of Medicine. In addition this subgroup contains historical sketches of MAC and other information gathered for MAC anniversaries and the centennial of the Medical Library Association.
  - Historical Information related to MAC
    - MAC/MLA Correspondence 1968 (Box-folder 6.6)
    - MAC/MLA Correspondence 1974 (Box-folder 6.7)
    - MAC/MLA Correspondence by Helen Brown Schmidt 1962-1972 (Box-folder 6.8)
      Correspondence from executive secretary of MLA.
    - MAC History Sources 1998 (Box-folder 6.9)
      This folder includes brief histories of the MAC MLA as well as photocopies of articles reporting on past annual meetings.
    - MAC History Marcia Noyes 1962-1971 (Box-folder 6.10)
      This folder includes correspondence and articles relating to the display honoring Marcia Noyes.
    - North Carolina's move from the Southern Chapter to MAC 1969 (Box-folder 6.11)
  - MAC/MLA Anniversaries n.d.
    - MAC Centennial celebration 1998 (Box-folder 6.24)
      Contains correspondence as well as Anatomy of a Chapter.
    - MAC Centennial panel 1998 (Box-folder 6.25)
      Correspondence and personal recollections.
    - Histories of chapter hospitals and libraries. (Box-folder 6.26)
      Includes the histories of many of the Hospitals and Libraries in the Chapter.
    - MAC birthday card 1998 (Box-folder 6.27)
      100th Anniversary Card
    - Mounted Labels and Photographs n.d. (Box-folder 6.28-29)
      From MAC History exhibits
    - MAC Anniversary Slide Show 2002, DVD movie slide show (Box-folder 6.30)